<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of militarie discipline</title>
            <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21904.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836074</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11654)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 819:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of militarie discipline</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iames Bryson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified as STC 811 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Armed forces --  Regulations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:318:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:318:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF MILITARIE DISCIPLINE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>When thou goest out to battell againſt thine enemies, bee not afraid of them, and keep thee from every wicked thing.</p>
               <bibl>Deut. 20.1. and 23.9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by Iames Bryſon, ANNO DOM. 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:318:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:318:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES <hi>OF MILITARIE</hi> DISCIPLINE.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note> I. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT in everie Regiment under a <hi>Collonell,</hi> there bee an eccleſiaſticall El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip or Kirke Seſſion, conſiſting of the Miniſter or Miniſters of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of Elders to be choſen to that effect; who ſhall ſit at their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed times, and judge in all Kirke affaires, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of GOD, and the rules and order of Diſcipline uſed in the Kirke of SCOTLAND for cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of delinquents, as fornicatours, whooremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, adulterers, ſwearers, curſers, drunkards, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faners of the Sabbath, and all ſcandalous perſons, that they may be brought to repentance: or being found obſtinat and incorrigible, that the extreame cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures of the Kirke paſſe againſt them. And that all things bee done herein, as in every paroſh in the time of peace. Alſo, that tender care may be had of the poore and needie, and of all ſuch as are not able, or may be diſabled to helpe themſelves: There bee ſome Deacons appointed in everie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:318:3"/>according to the order uſed in particular pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſhes and that in matter of greateſt weight, there be a generall Elderſhip, or common eccleſiaſtick judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, made up of all the Miniſters of the Camp, and of an Elder direct from every particular Regiment, who ſhall chooſe their own Moderatour and Clerk, have power to ſet down order in matters eccleſiaſticall for the whole Armie: that there may bee an uniformitie of worſhip and of Diſcipline. To whom appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may bee made from the inferiour Seſſions and elderſhips.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Courts of juſtice.</note> II. It is ordained alſo for deciding of all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and that the following articles of war and camp Diſcipline may be the better obſerved and obeyed. That there be in the Armie two courts of juſtice: one higher and another lower court: In every Regiment there ſhalbe a lower court, where the <hi>Collonell</hi> ſhal be preſident, and in his abſence his Leive-tenant, with them are two Captains to bee joyned, two Leive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, two Enſignes, foure Serjants, and two Quartermaſters, that together with the Preſident they may be to the number of thirteene at leaſt.</p>
            <p>In the high martiall court ſhall the generall bee Preſident, and in his abſence the field Marſchall, his aſſociats ſhall be the Generall of the ordinance, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant-major Generall, Generall of the horſes, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termaſter Generall, Muſter Maſters, and all the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels, or their Leivetenants in their abſence, all theſe ſhall ſit together every man in his owne place and ranke, whenſover there is any matter of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in controverſie both in the higher Court and lower, there ſhall be one ſworne Secretarie or Clerke appointed, who ſhall not only make note of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:318:3"/>and ſentences, but ſhall alſo make diligent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of all notable things that fall out in the armie, whither in any pitched battell, skirmiſh, leaguer, or any other piece of ſervice whatſoever, with all the circumſtances of time, place, or perſons; he ſhall alſo ſet his hand to all ſentences ſigned by the Generall, and keep a true regiſter of all interpriſes, that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall with his councel of war, ſhall give order to be done. It ſhall be lawfull alſo in all civill and crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall actions of great importance, to make appellation from the lower to the higher Court: The ſentence of the court ſhall bee publickly read in the hearing of all men, but not put in execution, till the Generall give command. No ſuperiour officer, Collonell, or Captaine, ſhall ſolicite for any man, that is lawfully convicted by the Court, either for any cryme, or for not obſerving the articles of warre, unleſſe it bee for his very neare kinſman for whom nature compelleth him to interceed; otherwiſe, the ſoliciter ſhall bee holden as odious as the Delinquent, at leaſt ſhalbe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered from his charge. The foreſaid judicatories as wel of the Kirk matters, as of war, ſhalbe ſubject to the councel of eſtate, and generall Aſſemblies <hi>reſpectivè.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The oath of the Iudges.</note> III. All the Iudges both of the higher and lower Court ſhall ſolemnly ſwear before GOD this folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oath:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="oath">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I N. N.</hi> Do here promiſe before God, that I both will and ſhall judge uprightly, in all things that ſhall be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Court, according to the law of God, the laws of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the articles of warre agreed upon, ſo farre as I have knowledge or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, neither will I for favour or hatred, for good will or evil will, for fear, for revenge, or for any gift or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:318:4"/>bribe whatſoever, judge wrongouſly, but judge him free that ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e free and doome him guiltie that I finde guiltie, as the great God the Lord of heaven and earth ſhall helpe me, and be my judge at the great day.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The oath of the officers and ſoule<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers.</note> IIII. All the officers and Souldiers that ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſhal with lifted up hands in all reverence ſwear this following oath.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="oath">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I N. N.</hi> do here promiſe and ſwear, that unto the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland</hi> I will be a faithfull ſervant according to the Covenant, and unto the Generall of the armie I will be a true and faithfull Souldier, everie manner of way doing my beſt endevours for the good of the Kingdome, and obedience of the Generall: to my power, alſo, ſhall I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all actions prejudiciall to the Kirk and Kingdome; and if I have tidings of any thing of that kinde I ſhall give notice thereof to ſome one or other of the councel of war. Moreover, I will doe my beſt to obſerve carefully all the Articles of warre, and points of camp Diſcipline: I ſhall behave my ſelfe manfully in battell, skirmiſhes, and every piece of ſervice in all times and places, when and where I ſhall be commanded: I ſhall keep watch and ward, and do all other dueties willingly, as I ſhall bee directed: I ſhall carrie my ſelfe obediently toward my ſuperiour officers, in all that they command me for the ſervice of the Kirke and Kingdome: In like maner, as I ſhall anſwer before God, and every honeſt man, I ſhall not flee from my Collours, or token whatſoever that I am commanded to follow, nor abſent my ſelf from them at any time, ſo long as I am able to go after them: I ſhall beſtow my life &amp; goods for advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of this ſervice of the Kingdome, and to the uttermoſt of my power endure all diſtreſſes, that can poſsibly fall out in the warres, fighting manfully to the very last, ſo farre forth as I am able, or that any true ſouldier ought to doe:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:318:4"/>Furthermore, if hereafter I be put into any place or charge by the Generall, or called to anie imployment, I ſhall doe my beſt endevour, valiantly and honeſtly to acquite my ſelf according to my place. This oath ſhall I well and truly keep, as the great God, the Lord of heaven and earth ſhall helpe me at the laſt judgement.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Prayers and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> V. For doing of ſervice and worſhip to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, the Lord of hoſts, for whoſe Covenant this war is under taken, from whom we look for aſſiſtance, and on whom the ſucceſſe of warre depends; it is thought neceſſary that there be publick prayers, every day morning and evening throughout the whole Leaguer, for which purpoſe, ſome token or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhall bee given by ſound of trumpet or drum. That on the Lords day there bee publick preaching, both before and afternoone, and if the time permit, two dayes in the week alſo. If any Miniſter ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect his time of prayer, or preaching, he ſhall for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very abſence forfault an halfe months pay, or as much as may be accounted an halfe months pay, to be taken up by the Deacons, &amp; at the direction of the Elderſhip to be diſtributed to the poore. And whatſoever ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſhall neglect the time of prayer or preaching, ſhall forfault a dayes wage for every abſence, and if after admonition by his Captaine he ſhall bee found guiltie of neglect or contempt, hee ſhall ly in priſon for the ſpace of twentie foure houres, and be further puniſhed, as his fault deſerveth.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">No mercat in time of divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</note> VI. There ſhall bee no mercat nor ſelling of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities whatſoever, after the warning is given for divine ſervice, till it be cloſed: and if any ſhall happen to contraveine, they ſhall make forfault of all things ſo ſold, whereof the one halfe ſhall be diſpoſed upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:318:5"/>by the Generall, or ſuch as ſhall be appointed by him, and the other half to be given to the Deacons for the uſe of the poore. Over and above which the offender ſhall for one whole day be put in priſon.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. All Officers and Souldiers ſhall be obedient unto the Generall and field-marſhall with other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers next under them, in whatſoever they ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand upon the paines following.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever behaveth not himſelf reverently and obediently unto the Generall of the Armie, ſhall be kept in yrons or priſon, till he be brought to anſwere before a councel of war, where being found guilty, whatſoever his qualitie be, hee ſhall ſtand to the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of the councell, to underly what puniſhment they ſhall thinke convenient according to his merite.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever ſhall offer to diſcredit theſe great offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers by word of mouth, or otherwiſe, and be not able by proofe to make it good; and whoſoever ſhall lift up any manner of armes againſt any of them, whither he doe them hurt or not, ſhall be puniſhed by death. And if any officer do ſtrick any of them with his hand, whither he hit or miſſe, he ſhall loſſe his right hand.</p>
            <p>If it ſhall hapen that the Generall, or any of the great and generall officers at any occaſion ſhall offer injurie to any noble man, knight, gentleman, or other which ſtandeth not with their honour to put up, Then ſhall they give in their complaint to the Councel of war, where the offender ſhall anſwer, and bee cenſured ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the qualitie and importance of the fault.</p>
            <p>If any Souldier or inferior officer ſerving on horſe or foot, ſhall offer any injurie by word, or deed, to his Collonell, Leivetenant Collonell, Sergeant ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jour, Quarter-maſter, Captain or any of his ſuperiors,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:318:5"/>or ſhall refuſe any dewty commanded him, he ſhall be puniſhed according to the importance of his fault, and if it ſhall happen that any officer ſhall command any thing which tendeth rather to the prejudice nor to the good of the publick, then ſhall he who is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded modeſtly refuſe to obey and preſently give notice thereof.</p>
            <p>If any inferiour officer ſhal challenge any common Souldier to be guilty of any diſhoneſt action, he ſhall anſwer for it before the court as if he were his equall.</p>
            <p>If any Souldier horſe or foot, ſhall offer to ſtrike his officer that commands him any dewty or piece of ſervice, he ſhal loſe his hand and be turned out of the quarter, and if it be done in any fort or beleaguered place after the watch is ſet, he ſhal loſe his life for it; but if he not only offer but do hurt to any of them, whether in the field, or not he ſhall be ſhot to death.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever in the preſence of the Generall ſhall draw his ſword to do miſchief with it, ſhall loſe his hand: He who ſhal in anger draw his ſword, while his Colloures are fleeing, either in batell or in march, ſhall be ſhot to death: He who ſhall preſume to draw his ſword in any court of juſtice, ſhall loſe his life: He that draws his ſword in any ſtrength or fort to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chief therewith after the watch is ſet, ſhal loſe his life.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obedience to the marſhalls.</note> VIII. The Proveſt-marshall-general may apprehend any man by his own authority &amp; keep him in irones or in priſon, but by no means may do execution upon him although he be ſentenced by the court of war, without firſt giving notice thereof to the Generall and obtaining warrand for that effect.</p>
            <p>The ſame is to be underſtood of the Proveſt-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shals of every regiment and companie: And if anie ſhall be found to hinder the Proveſt-marſhals when
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:318:6"/>they are to apprehend any man or when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to execute any thing that becomes them, they ſhall not eſcape unpuniſhed in the martiall court.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Puniſhment of ſwearers, drunkards, &amp;c.</note> IX Common &amp; ordinarie profainers of the ſabbath, ſwearers and drunkards, eſpecially ſuch as ſhall be found drinking in time of prayers or divine ſervice, ſhall not only be puniſhed in their means, but ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make their publick repentance in the midſt of the congregation, and if they cannot be reclaimed, they ſhall be caſheired and diſcharged as unworthy to do ſervice in any place of the armie.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Duells and combats forbiden.</note> X No duell or combate ſhall be permitted to be foughten; If any man offer wrong to another, it ſhall bee decided by the officers of the regiment, the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenger ſhall anſwer it before the Martiall court. And if any Captaine, Leivtenant or other inferiour officer ſhall give leave or permiſſion unto any under their command to enter combate, and doth not rather hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, he ſhall be preſently caſheired from his charge and ſerve afterward as a common Souldiour: but if any harme be done he ſhall anſwer it as deeply as he that did it.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">No forceing of women, nor ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of whoores.</note> XI He that forceth any woman and the matter be proved, he ſhall die for it.</p>
            <p>No whoore ſhall be ſuffered in the leaguer, but if any will have his own wife with him, he may.</p>
            <p>If any man keep an unmaried woman, he ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther marrie her or be conſtrained to put her away, and make his repentance for his fault.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of muſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> XII All Souldiers ſhall dewly repaire unto the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall muſters upon the day and houre appointed, nor ſhall any Colonell or Captaine of horſe or foot keep back his Souldiers from being muſtered at the time when the muſter maſters ſhall deſire to view them, if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:318:6"/>any refuſe, he ſhall be holden for a mutiner.</p>
            <p>No Colonell or Captaine ſhall lend any of their Souldiers unto another upon the muſterdays for the making up of their numbers compleat: he that thus makes a falſe muſter, ſhal anſwer it at a martiall court, where being found guilty he ſhall be proclaimed a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaver, after which being put out of the quarter his Colours ſhall flee no more.</p>
            <p>If any horſman borrowes either horſe, armour, piſtols, ſadle, ſword or harniſe to paſſe the muſter withall, ſo much as is borrowed ſhal be eſchited, and both himſelf and he that lent it him, ſhall be turned out of the leaguer, the one half of the armes forfaulted ſhall go unto the Captaine, and the other half unto the Perforce.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> XIII. When any march is to be made, every man that is ſworn ſhal follow his colours, whoſoever preſumes without leave to ſtay behinde, ſhal be puniſhed.</p>
            <p>If any upon mutinie be found to do it, be they many or be they few, they ſhall die for it.</p>
            <p>Every man is to keep his own rank and file upon the march, and not to put others from their ordour, nor ſhall any man caſt himſelf behinde, or ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon any wagon or horſeback: The offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be puniſhed according to the time and place.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> XIV. He that after warning is given by ſound of Drum or Trumpet for ſetting of the watch, doth wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abſent himſelf without ſome lawfull excuſe, ſhall be diſgraced and be put to bread and water, or ſome ſuch puniſhment as the matter is of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>He that is taken ſleeping upon the watch to the indangering of the armie, ſhall be ſhot to death.</p>
            <p>In like ſort ſhall he be puniſhed who drinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:318:7"/>drunk upon his watch or place of ſentinell that he cannot do his dewty, or that cometh off his watch where he is commanded to keep his guaird.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reteir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> XV. Whatſoever regiment ſhall once charge the enemie, and then retire afterward from them before they come to dint of ſword, ſhaIl anſwer it before the high martiall court: and if this be occaſioned by any officer, he ſhall be publickly diſgraced, and turned out of the leaguer: If the fault ſhall be found to be in the Souldiers, then ſhall every tenth man be hanged and the reſt condemned to carry all the filth out of the leaguer, till by ſome exploit they procure their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and recover their reputation; provided alwaies, if at the firſt any man can by the teſtimony of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent witneſſes prove himſelf not guilty of the couard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, he ſhall go free.</p>
            <p>If any occaſion be to enter any ſtrength or ſconce by aſſault or breach, he who reteires from the place before he hath been at handy blows with the enemy &amp; hath uſed his ſword ſo far as it is poſſible for him to do ſervice with it and before he be by maine ſtrength beaten off by the enemy, ſhall be ſo puniſhed as the court ſhall finde him to have deſerved.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of fleeing and couard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</note> XVI. Whoſoever runs from his Collours and doeth not defend them to the uttermoſt of his power ſo long as they be in danger, ſhall ſuffer death for it.</p>
            <p>When any occaſion of ſervice is, he that firſt runs away, if any man kill him he ſhall be free, and if at that time he eſcape and be apprehended afterward, he ſhal be proclaimed traitour &amp; put out of the quarter.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever enſigne-bearer ſhall flee out of any place of Battrie, ſconce or redoubt before he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured three aſſaults and receives no relieif, ſhall be in like manner puniſhed, providing alwayes the place be defenceable.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:318:7"/>
            <p>If any regiment, troup or companie ſhall flee out of the field or battell, they ſhall anſwer for it before the high court, and if there it can be proved to have broken their oath, they ſhall be proclaimed traitours.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of treating with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie.</note> XVII. Whatſoever regiment, troupor companie ſhall be found to treat with the enemie or to enter in any conditions with them, without knowledge and leave of the Generall or chief commander in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the officer ſhall be put to death for it and all his goods confiſcated; of the Souldiers every tenth man ſhall be hanged and the reſt puniſhed as is a foreſaid.</p>
            <p>But if any that then were in companie of ſuch can free themſelves from being partakers of the crime and can prove that they did their beſt to reſiſt it, then ſhall they be rewarded according to their truth and faithfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever gives advice unto the enemy any manner of way or keeps any diſcourſe with him with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out leave of the Generall, or giveth unto him any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intelligence by letters or otherwaies or maks any ſigne unto him for his advantage ſhall die for it.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of giving up of ſtrengths.</note> XVIII. They that give over any ſtrength to the enemy, unleſſe it be for extremity of hunger or want of amunition, the governour with all the officers ſhal die for it: All the Souldiers be lodged without the quarter and be made to carry all the filth out of the leaguer, till by ſome new proof of their worth they blot away the former cowardice.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of mutinie.</note> XIX. If any numbers of Souldiers ſhal without leave of their Captaine aſſemble together for raking muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous counſell amongſt themſelves, ſo many inferior officers as be in company with them ſhal ſuffer death, and the Souldiers be ſo puniſhed, as they that give up any ſtrength: And whatſoever Captaine ſhall permit
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:318:8"/>unto his Souldiers to hold any ſuch meetings amongſt themſelves, ſhall anſwer it before the high court of juſtice.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall fall in quarrelling, and fighting and ſhal call for help of his friends or familiars with intention to be revenged or to defend himſelf, he ſhall ſuffer death for it, and they that come to help him ſhall be puniſhed like mutiners.</p>
            <p>He alſo ſhall be reckned for a mutiner who ſhall not be content with that quarter or place that ſhall be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him, whither in a town or in the leaguer.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The keeping of armes.</note> XX Whoſoever caſts his arms from him either in the field or other where, ſhall be ſcourged through the quarter &amp; diſgraced as before, til he redeem his credit.</p>
            <p>He that ſels or enpawnes his armes or any kinde of amunition, or any ſpades, ſhools, picks, &amp; other the like neceſſary inſtruments uſed in the field, ſhal be for the firſt and ſecond time beaten through the quarter, and for the third time, puniſhed as for other thift: He alſo that buyes or taks them upon pawne, be he Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier or be he victualer, he ſhall both looſe his money and be puniſhed as he that ſold them.</p>
            <p>He that wilfully breaks any of his armes or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments aforeſaid, ſhall not only pay for the mending of them, but ſhall be put to bread and water, and ſhal be puniſhed otherwiſe at the diſcretion of the court.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Againſt fire.</note> XXI. No man ſhal preſume to ſet on fire any town or village in the land or camp, if any doeth he ſhall be puniſhed according as the judges ſhall finde the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter important.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. Billets and lodgings in every place muſt be directed by the quarter-maſter or quarter-maſter generally; No commander or common Souldier shall exact or extort any thing beſides what is appointed.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:318:8"/>
            <p>All muſt deal courteouſly with their hoſte and his houshold ſervants: He that beats any of them, for the firſt and ſecond fault he shall be put in irones and made to faſt with bread and water, but if he do any of them greater hurt he shall be punished at the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the court.</p>
            <p>None shall preſume to do wrong to any that bring neceſſaries unto the leaguer, whither by taking their goods or by taking away their horſes; which who ſo doeth shal be ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
            <p>They that pillage or ſteal any thing, whither from them that furnish the leaguer or from uther ſubjects of the kingdome, whither Covenanters or not Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, they shall be punished as for other thift.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the ſpoil and pillage.</note> XXIII. If it ſo pleaſe God that we beat the enemy either in the field or in the leaguer, no man shall fall upon the pillage till the enemy be utterly put to the rout; which done, every man may fall upon his own quarter and reſt contented with it, without plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of others: If any man shal fall upon the pillage before the time, and any evill to the armie shall enſue upon their greedineſſe after the ſpoile, then shall all of them ſuffer death for it, and although no damnage come thereby, yet muſt they be punished as their fault deſerveth.</p>
            <p>When any fort or place of ſtrength is taken in, no man shall fall upon the ſpoile before the enemy be beaten out of all his holds and the quarters be dealt out and aſſigned.</p>
            <p>If any be found drunk in the enemies leaguer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath forſaken the ſame and laid down his armes, he shall be ſeverly punished according to the damnage done by his drunkenneſſe, and although there be no damnage, yet shal he be puniſhed for his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:318:9"/>drunkenneſſe, eſpecially at ſuch a time.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of pay.</note> XXIV. No Captaine shall with-hold any off his Souldiers meanes from him, which if he do, he shall be cenſured in the court of juſtice; And if any ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil follow thereupon, as that the Souldiers mutine, be ſicke, endure hunger, or give up any ſtrength, then shall he be anſwerable for all theſe inconveniences.</p>
            <p>If any Captaine lend money unto his Souldiers which he will have payed again, let it be repayed in parcels as the Souldier may ſpare it, that the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſervice be no wayes hindered or neglected thereby.</p>
            <p>If upon neceſſity it come to paſſe, pay be not made at the due time, yet shall every man be forward in his ſervice all having victuals for the preſent &amp; certaine expectation of the meanes ſo ſoon as may be.</p>
            <p>No Captaine shall preſume to go out of his ſtation to demand his pay without leave of the Generall, providing he be intertained: who ſo doth shall be caſheired from his place.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of paſses.</note> XXV. No Colonell or Captaine shall give leave to his Souldiers to go home out of the field, without leave of the Generall or chief commander, under the paine of the looſe of three Monethes pay, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it before the court.</p>
            <p>No Souldier shall deſire his paſſe, whileſt there is any preſent ſervice to be done againſt the enemie.</p>
            <p>If any Souldier deſire to be diſcharged from the wars becauſe he is ſick, or maimed, or upon any ſuch reaſonable cauſe, he ſhall be diſcharged by warrand from the Generall.</p>
            <p>If any Souldier ſhal run away from his Collours, without a paſſe of his officers, he ſhall be apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where ever he can be found and puniſhed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the articles foreſaid.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:318:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
